[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host jeff doolittle i'm excited
to invite jerome labon as our guest on
the show today for a conversation about
cross-platform ui jerome labond has been
programming since 1998 and is a
microsoft mvp
jerome has been mainly involved in
dot-net and c-sharp development as a
teacher
trainer and consultant in france he is
the cto of uno platform in montreal the
first and only c-sharp xaml platform for
single code-based applications that run
on windows webassembly ios mac os
android and linux which i think covers
pretty much everything so welcome to the
show jerome
hi jeff thanks for inviting me yeah glad
you could be here
so today we're going to be talking about
cross-platform ui
so let's start what's the problem space
and why is there a need for user
interfaces that can run on multiple
platforms
the
the industry has been trying to chase
that
tale for quite a while and
the
the big problem is is all about skill
set and your duplication of issues and
you know being able to reproduce
anything or having
different teams different silos and
things like that so trying to get
teams to be able to
reuse as much as they can across
platforms without having to
be impacted by the underlying platform
underlying platform as much as possible
and depending on what you're targeting
that can be very difficult in some cases
you know if you're trying to get to you
know let's say ios and android those two
can be very different when you're trying
to get to the ui and
and into
most extents
same thing goes for a non-ui api so if
you want to go to geo location or things
like that and it's very difficult to get
to something that that works across
platforms there's a web that tries to do
this with you know getting a
cross-platform so it is running
everywhere but still is the web in many
cases you know still javascript the
performance issues but you know it's
ubiquitous
but there are no stores for the web so
that's nice but if you go to ios and
android there there's a store
but the development environment is very
nice new quite fast because it's running
on devices
there's all sorts of things like this
though so the idea about cross-platform
and trying to get there is to have one
single code base in most cases
and trying to adjust
for the underlying
or i mean in some of the the supporting
products let's say trying to get to
something that's 100
reusable and you with its advantages and
disadvantages and in some other cases
trying to get to as much as possible
being reused and then
use the underlying platform
when needed to get let's say out of the
box so we can discuss about that
afterwards but the idea is that you have
to choose between those you know
different scenarios with regards to apis
yeah and there's a lot you covered there
as far as developer skill sets for
example which platforms they need to
know and i imagine in a large company
that can afford the funding they could
have different teams that know different
platforms and languages more than others
but of course then there's still
coordination issues if you want
consistency and so either way it's all
going to be trade-offs at the end of the
day between developer productivity
fidelity for what you want your product
to
look like and how users are going to
interact with it
and so obviously those are just some of
the many challenges and maybe in in a
bit more of the details you know you've
been doing this for a long time so i
know there's a lot of design
considerations that can make
cross-platform applications a challenge
so maybe what are some of those specific
things that teams might face just from a
design standpoint when they're trying to
adopt
you know an application delivery model
that lets them as you said reuse
code and reuse applications that are
going to work on different platforms
from the same code base
two sides of that coin so the if you
want to reuse the code then that means
that you're going to have to
make sure that the platforms you're
going to be trying to use is going to
cover as much as you can as much as
possible
from what the underlying platforms are
going to be providing so there are two
ways for doing this the first one is
lowest common denominator so that means
that you're going to get something that
looks the same behaves the same
at the expense of what the underlying
platform is able to provide and that's a
big problem because if you're on ios
then you may expect let's say
a text box
or an input control to behave in a
specific way because the platform is
behaving in a specific way and even more
so in in some cases you want to you want
to do let's say
accessibility for instance accessibility
is one big problem and if you're
ignoring what the platform provides then
you're going to get
all sorts of issues with regards to apis
and may not be there for doing what the
platform provides so let's say you want
to do screen reading then you may be
having some issues there so if you're
trying to get to something that's lowest
common and the lowest common denominator
then you're going to get into trouble
for those kind of things then there's
the other way around if you're you're
trying to get access to everything that
the platform provides then
then you get you can get into some of
the weird parts where
you can't
have the branding that you want and then
let's say
the button on ios doesn't
allow you to have something that looks
like the button from your company and
that your designers want so that's the
kind of things that makes it a bit
difficult in terms of ux wise now
if you go down a little bit then there's
the access to the platform apis let's
say if you want to do well i talked
about your location before so if you
want to do geolocation if you
go for the lowest common denominator
then you may you may have access to
parts of the the apis that are that the
underlying system provides or you may
have to design your apis yourself and
try to do the abstraction yourself and
if you do that then you may have some
issues when you're adding a third
platform for instance which has a
different set of apis and we're talking
again about dual location one of that
specific part of geolocation is user
consent for accessing the digital
location so that's kind of things that
need to be thought of in terms of of api
and choosing whether you want to reuse
or use a cross-platform framework or
develop your application directly on the
system using
what the platform provider suggests you
to use whether it's the web or ios
android or or any other
like windows
yeah absolutely and you know this leads
to what so many of these conversations i
think end up pointing to which is that
even something like cross-platform user
interface frameworks of course we're
going to talk about uno and others today
those are tools and if you run for the
tool without asking some of these
broader questions
then
you can blame the tool but i would
suggest you shouldn't blame the tool
because it's really a design question
you know you've mentioned in some of
your answer before it's sort of like
here's the idioms of this platform
versus what are the idioms say of our
design and our product team and and
which end of the spectrum do we want to
be there
to what extent are we okay with more
generalized layouts maybe versus being
pixel perfect and again that's going to
depend on really what you're building
you know if it's a an enterprise
application you'll make one set of
choices but if it's a game you're going
to make you know very different choices
exactly game is because the game is
another interesting scenario and it's
very different i don't know we don't go
into the gaming specifically because it
has its own set of very specific
constraints but with regards to the
choices that you need to make in terms
of you're getting your application there
running on on all those platforms i
think it's all about reuse and making
sure that you don't spend cycles just
repeating the same i would say mistakes
but it's the
the bad side of the coin but you're
repeating the same process and and
having a you know different set of
customers that asking different things
and then the interpretation of what the
the designers and
whichever architect type of person may
be there to decide what's there and that
may or may not have a familiarity with
the platforms that are being discussed
with with the overall architecture so
let's say if you're doing a simple
application or a very you know that has
a vertical that it's quite simple in a
sense let's say you uber
you could probably
do something that's you know fairly
explicit for each platform because you
want the the experience to be fine-tuned
to the to the to the maximum extent
possible for the platform and that's
probably fine if you're spending
let's say five times
the money on developing an application
there but not everyone's able to do this
unfortunately and
new
application development in general is is
it was expensive and it's getting more
expensive by the month that are passing
by for a variety of reasons so
it doesn't make sense to
waste inner energy
in redeveloping things particularly if
your core business is
not necessarily the ui
but
everything that's in between
and developing all this may be very very
expensive absolutely and it's
interesting you see it's getting more
expensive because most things in
technology were used to them getting
less expensive over time
and yet it seems that this is a space
where we're wrestling with that and
hopefully tools like what we're going to
be talking about today can be part of
the answer to some solutions there for
for companies where it makes sense so
maybe digging a little deeper into some
of these technical and organizational
issues that make cross-platform
applications uniquely difficult
it's one thing to say i want this device
to run on android and ios it's another
thing to say i want to have the same app
run on android ios and web and desktop
oh by the way linux desktop 2 please
and i guess i'd start with is that even
a good idea
exactly i think the answer is maybe some
it's the consultant answer right it
depends but talk with us a little bit
about that challenge and then maybe we
could dig into it into a couple others
the first question that comes up is for
most people that are trying to do this
and we've been trying so i've been a
developer for mobile apps for a very
long time let's say something like
11 12 years now so it takes me back a
bit and trying to do that kind of reuse
across platform and things like that and
what do you do when your application can
span from a let's say i'm going to take
the extreme but
a smart watch
to you know a 100 inches screen
that's touch for some reason
how do you make an application that
resizes that much and scales across all
those screens so
if i trim down a little bit the the
question is i have my app running on the
web and then i have my app running on
mobile
how do i make my ui react
between those two the non-good question
is scale the ui that's not the good
thing to do especially down to your
watch from 100 you know inch screen yeah
exactly so that doesn't work so then you
can do things like readjust your ui new
let's say
instead of being horizontal you go
vertical and then you can change things
like removing columns removing data have
burger menus that expand and resize but
then you have issues like you know let's
say
you're on an ipad for instance
and then
an ipad and even in normal apps you know
you don't even have to go to a large
screen let's say your ipad allows you to
put things on the site you know i think
it goes
called snap or something on ios and
change multiple times names but anyways
the idea is that your application is
opened you have navigated to something
let's say you you're in a let's say
master detail view then you click on
your master then you go to detail
then you're in full view then you take
your app and put it on the side
suddenly you only have
a third of the size
for your app what do you do
do you
show the details do you show
the master
if you're in the details if you go back
what does it do if you if you're in the
master but then you selected something
it has some ui cues with it then what do
you do what do you change so that's kind
of the kind of design
consideration to have an ux to take into
account when designing your application
and in many cases
people decide to just not support that
because they don't have the budget for
it and they say
my app doesn't resize or it supports
desktop and it's ui rich or data rich
and i don't care if it goes down to
a mobile-sized device the other way
around is
i care a new about mobile and form
factor it can resize you know rescale a
little bit
because of the size of the screen and
things like that but if you put it on
let's say an ipad it's going to be it's
going to look awful in most cases or
they're just going to shrink everything
and put it in the middle so that's the
kind of consideration that you need to
have when you're trying to get an
application to run
across multiple platforms and then and
then it goes
if you're talking about very large
screen then touch then you know you can
have we we you know we support console
input devices so it can be remote
control it can be mouse a touch a pen
and things like many things that can
influence the development of your
application and it can get quite
difficult to get there so that's the
taste of things that need to be
considered when going across platforms
yeah and i imagine even with the tools
that can allow you to do cross-platform
all the things on every platform you
still have to make the design decision
about whether that is the right thing to
do maybe that makes sense to do a
desktop and web and even though the tool
might allow you to do mobile you might
decide that we're not going to use the
tool to do that for now but that's
that's going to be up to you as a team
it's just sometimes people see a tool
and you know it's like the swiss army
knife that has 50 different things on it
and they want to use them all it's like
well all we really need is these three
so let's just do this and we can do this
so i i'm curious in your experience
though if that kind of desire to use
everything about the tool sometimes
bites people as well in this space
well money comes back
always so
yes ultimately let's say the developer
or the architect or whichever the
someone that's that position is going to
say i want to target everything because
me we don't want to have anyone left
behind but the problem is that new
development costs even if the the
tooling allows you to do cross-platform
development you still have to test on
every single platform to make sure that
it works properly and in in many
scenarios so the one that comes back
often is accessibility and for
regulatory purposes in many cases you
you need to have that enabled and
it may behave differently in some cases
and your platform or your ap your
framework may not be able to handle
all the scenarios that you want to have
or maybe visually it's not doing the
right thing or maybe
you know some platforms do support you
know suspending your application or
killing your application in ways you
can't expect and let's say you're on
linux on windows your application is
going to run as long as it's not closed
but and you in unless terminated
explicitly but it's hard for a user to
do that but on ios and android
i mean the application can be stopped at
any time because the os decides so so
that's the kind of things that need to
be thought of when doing your
development and going across all those
targets can be difficult so the
framework the underlying framework tries
to help you there with providing all the
hooks in a cross-platform way but it's
not always possible because sometimes
they don't exist or they're not
available or you know they don't map to
anything that's cross-platform-e e in in
a way
yeah absolutely and now we're getting
sort of some of the behind-the-scenes
things as well you know having done a
lot of mobile development myself in my
career and just you're mentioning some
of the life cycling differences between
say ios and android and even the ways
they handle when are we going to
background an application and then when
are we going to
basically shut it down but then also
what mechanisms are we can allow for
caching state so that if you restart the
app it looks like it didn't shut down so
that to the user
it looks like a seamless experience but
you're saving resources and battery and
this sort of thing but the way they do
it is different too so that's where i
imagine these cross-platform tools it's
not just about the user experience and
the user interface it's also about how
do you manage these different
life cycling patterns and and other
things and what else might there be in
that regard that the teams might
struggle with you know there's the life
cycling thing but you know what else as
far as platform specificity have you
seen be things that teams need to
consider well a lot of them you know we
can go from memory management to cpu
architectures the weirdest one that i
got was
some android devices that i have
heterogeneous cpus so some cores go fast
some others don't
and then you can do weird stuff because
you're having that kind of thing so if
you assume that your api is able to do
some things on a at a certain speed
because
because you're doing it that way then if
you don't have a cpu affinity then
you're going to have stuff like that
looks like that or you can have all
sorts of touch speed issues or animation
issues because your devices have a
certain style or you can have local
issues on you let's say a specific
variant of a specific device that runs
on a specific country behaves a certain
way that no other device does so that's
the kind of things that can be happening
when you're developing so you know it
adds up to all the things that need to
be considered when testing your devices
across platform even if you're using the
same code that runs everywhere you know
there's keyboard input can you actually
use an actual keyboard new physical
keyboard mouse input can you use a mouse
on an ios device yes you can and if you
can then
that means that you're going to be able
to do things that you cannot do with a
finger so things like this you know if
you have a mouse that means that you can
have a hover
and hover states on a button
and needs to do a specific thing so you
know it's not something that you add
after after the fact if you have a
keyboard that means you have focus so i
mean you have to have focus hints and
then you keep tab multiple times then
which controller you're on and if you if
you're only on a touch device you can't
do focus because you're on a control or
you're not so that's the kind of things
that makes it different and then
there are platforms that don't have
threading for instance if you're going
webassembly you know threading is very
very new and in some cases you can do
threads or you can't do file system
access or you can't do
lots of things that you can or can't do
and you have to take into account the
fact that it may not be available when
you're developing your application so
the last one that i got was you know i'm
on the web and i want to open a pdf file
in a pdf viewing application that's on
my my device how do i do that
the browsers don't allow you to do this
you have to download the file then open
it that's kind of things that you can do
on a mobile phone you can do on a
desktop you're using a native app that
you can't do on the web so
user flow are different depending on the
target that you're on as you're talking
about all of these
heterogeneous approaches to things and
all the various things we would want to
do you know in these kinds of
applications it occurs to me too how
important it is for a design team to
understand the capabilities
of the platform that you're targeting
and that you're dealing with
can a cross-platform framework like uno
help with that kind of aspect of the
conversation with design teams and if so
how have you seen that work
in terms of getting access to the
features of the platform
uno is based on the
uwp api so the two parts of uwp which is
not supposed to be used anymore no it's
uwp is trying to get it to to win ui but
we can get into the detail but the idea
is that we have two parts the first part
is winrt it's a set of apis that have
been developed since windows 8. so
working on iot devices up to
large surface wall things i don't
remember the names so the idea is that
all those apis cover
the absence or presence of things
available on those devices
and that means that because uno is
implementing those apis and providing
access to those in a cross-platform way
we're able to
let's say provide a way for developers
to know
what's possible what's not possible and
then make that bubble up to the design
to say you're you're on that platform
that is not possible so we have to find
a way to
surface that and somehow so let's say
you want to share a file is it possible
on that platform or not you know do we
show the button do we we say that we
change the behavior to say you know send
by email or use a server-side component
to do something
considerations in that sense so
in terms of what uno is trying to
provide it's trying to give access to as
much as
the underlying features of the platform
based on what microsoft already thought
of in terms of api design
when they designed it originally
for windows 8 windows phone and others
because they had that breadth of devices
at the time
kind of reaping the benefits of this in
a sense because we're implementing those
apis
and we're talking about screen resizing
and things like that they thought about
that using what are called adaptive
triggers so let's say you you trigger
your your ui to say
when the screen size is that
length then do that thing if it's less
than that do the other thing if it's on
a low power device then do that thing
and if it's on the web do that other
thing visually that's the kind of things
that is possible so you can go down to
specifics but then overall
it's
mostly about determining from your
design perspective
what can i do on the set of platforms
that i want to target and
it's not because uno targets all the
platforms that you can see that you have
to target all those platforms at once
because it may not be
possible or money efficient for you to
target all those platforms considering
the set of apis that you want to use
that's the biggest question that you
have to have yourself ask yourself when
developing and designing your
application now to be clear you
mentioned uwp which i believe is
universal windows platform
is that correct and just to be clear
you're describing uno platform when you
talk about those apis being implemented
but you're not saying that because it
uses universal windows platform or or
winrt apis that you are
building a windows or winrt enable or a
windows only application it's not you've
found in your solution and we can talk a
little bit more about this as the show
continues about the different approaches
that people have taken and the teams
have taken to solving this issue of
cross-platform ui but to summarize this
i think what i'm hearing you say is
the uno platform team looked at the apis
that microsoft created for the universal
windows platform and said these are good
apis and they're even more generalizable
beyond just windows
and if so you've adopted those apis
really as an abstraction but then you've
created your own implementation around
those abstractions that allows you now
to deliver for linux android ios windows
and web
that's exactly that and
the important part is that we don't have
to design anything specifically because
you know designing apis is very
difficult you know when people you know
they spent i don't know how much this
spent but it must have been painful to
design all this and
the idea behind all this is to say yes
it's called uwp at that point so why
previously uwp and now we split it into
its winrt apis and win ui api so when ui
is just all about
showing things on the screen and when rt
is all about manipulating the system so
file access network you know sharing
things opening files saving files things
like that so that's the
any any kind of sensors that you want to
get access to
all the i o stuff right
pretty much pretty much the i o yes i o
and system access in general
and those apis were well defined and
what we did is basically
extract the apis for this and
incrementally implement
those apis as we go and depending on on
what our clients are asking when going
on to our github so that's the idea for
this and yes it's definitely an
abstraction so
it has its advantages and disadvantages
you know if you're making abstraction
then you may be hiding things from the
developer so that's why generally we we
do
provide access to the underlying apis
that we're we're using as well and
that's what the net team has been doing
with original xamarin and now continuing
on 2.6 is that
it's not an abstraction in terms of
you're developing with c-sharp but you
get access to all the apis that are
available
underneath so we're talking about ios
and android in this case yeah you get
access to everything so if what we're
doing in uno that does let's say
geo location or vibration device access
is not suiting you in any in any way
then you can just drop you know not use
what we're doing and then just go
directly to the the system apis to do
that yourself so that that works as well
now you lose obviously the fact that
it's going to be cross-platform because
if you're developing for ios then it
won't work in webassembly obviously but
that's the idea so
some of the
apis that were developed on on let's say
on the web you know their javascript
apis because it's it's about it's all
about running for webassembly and
webassembly doesn't have specifically
those apis so you have to go through
javascript to implement that so there's
all sorts of things that need to be
implemented there to get there so the
safest way for most people is to use the
abstractions because they don't want to
learn about the intricacies and
differences about those apis and rely on
what we've been doing but if for some
reason there's something that doesn't
work or you know it's not fine enough in
terms of access then it's possible to
work around it yeah it makes sense the
power outlet in your wall is a great
abstraction
on rare occasions you need to get around
that abstraction
but we really hope you know what you're
doing when you do that exactly
and so these abstractions have been
adopted here and that sounds like that's
some aspects of that i imagine are
similar across the different
cross-platform frameworks but let's
maybe step back and take a little walk
down memory lane and give us some
context for how we've arrived at where
we are because cross-platform ui in some
sense i think has felt like a holy grail
to people for for quite a while
and i believe the iphone came out in
either 07 or o8
and that's really when smartphones
became actually smart i mean i had a
little pocket pc phone and it was
definitely i would not call it a
smartphone i'd call it a dumb phone with
with a little bit of touch screen and a
little stylus but since then things have
definitely transformed significantly
so you and i both been in this space for
a long time and i'd love to just hear
from you
what's gone well and what have been
maybe spectacular struggles or failures
along the way
and then that can lead into now how are
those things being addressed now
well so much has changed
you know the iphone changed quite a bit
and by pushing
some technologies out and forcing some
in the most spectacular one was were
actually two in the same space where
civil light and flash
those two were pushed out because of the
iphone and ios was not allowing for many
reasons and for good reasons that you
know the rest of the industry took in
that in it took under its wing later on
but was the security aspect of it in
performance considerations and those two
what kind of an attempt at doing
cross-platform ui in a sense because you
were able to run your flash
i wouldn't say mostly everywhere but at
least you were able to do on linux to
some extent than mac and and windows so
that's the three major ones that were
there at the time
but still it was rendered ui from most
of the content so it was its own thing
on the web specifically but not really
on the web it was native inside of a web
browser so it wouldn't it wouldn't show
properly on the other ones then it got
pushed out
and it kind of pushed html in the front
for many reasons because you know
devices were slow and on the web you
could do some interesting things with
javascript and then or ajax at the time
and then you kind of moved to some
interesting
web development that was quite
interesting so what i would say is
in terms of getting all those
evolutions to get to the point where we
are now is that at the time getting
cross-platform was not really
a point it was just you know i want to
run the multiple os's more than multiple
form factors now we're talking about
getting to different devices and you
know completely different environments
you know crossing the web devices and
iot devices and things like that so it's
kind of a very wide range of things
and because of that diversity and
microsoft failed spectacularly you know
as a result of this
and because of the costume we were in
the middle of this for quite a while
when developing windows 1 applications
was the fact that people were saying now
we do have ios and android or
they have their flaws but you know they
still work and there's there's a
community and there's a lot of users
around it and amazon failed in that and
that's respect in the same way but
you're trying to get your applications
to run on something else than ios and
android then you get banned down again
to the cost do i want to maintain my
applications
on an additional device you know and
have a set of developers that
don't do the same things
and you know it comes down to just
everyone trying to enhance
and get their platform to be available
somehow besides the big ones and gets
difficult
so it's
repeating history in a sense yeah and
you know back to what you said before
about it getting more expensive it makes
sense because you alluded to the fact
that in the quote-unquote early days
that what we're dealing with is how do i
run this on multiple operating systems
but you're pretty much dealing with two
chip sets back then you got power pc and
you got intel amd which is the same x86
architecture so they're pretty much
dealing with two
and then beyond that what you're really
contending with now is the different
operating system implementations on top
of that architecture but there are only
so many screen sizes there were only so
many cpu speeds there were only so many
uh this and that and now you get into
all the different form factors that have
their own way of doing things and the
operating systems on them which aren't
always as unique as maybe they could be
although there are efforts with things
like pine phone and framework laptops to
sort of get us back to more user control
over those sorts of things and i'll put
links to the show notes to those
projects
but all that to sum up and say
no wonder it's getting more complex
we're trying to do more with more things
and those more things keep changing and
it keeps throwing new stuff at us
and so previous attempts to do things
like flash or
silver light or you remember the old
java apple maps
yeah and the job apps would spin you
know and say loading java and and that
that sort of a thing and yet ironically
you know it's java that runs from an
android but it's different than it was
then it's just the language we're
talking about the ui you know the
distinctive ui of java applets at the
time oh yes distinctive is a good way of
putting it yes
yeah so it's been a lot of approaches so
let's maybe shift now and say all right
with all of that to some extent the more
things change the more they stay the
same we just have more complexity to
deal with now so what are some of the
different approaches to cross-platform
ui you've mentioned a couple microsoft
has xamarin which is moving towards
something called maui we've talked about
uno a little bit what else is out there
and what kind of characterizes them and
differentiates some of those different
approaches
well let's say there are three ways for
rendering things so we were talking
about the ui specifically there are
three ways to do it pretty much if we're
talking specifically about class
platform things
so there are
frameworks that do pretty much
take the ui from the underlying system
and lay it out in such a way that
you can use cross-platform
tooling to lay out your native items in
the way you want
so that means that if you want to
display a checkbox a text box a button
or something like that then
all of this is going to be looking like
what the ui provides underneath and then
if you go on another system it's going
to be laid out
closely to the same
but no may not be exactly the same so
you may need to go into some length to
line everything properly and then your
designer is going to be you know saying
oh is that checkbox not looking the same
because at that location i wanted this
then it looks differently when running
on ios or on the web or things like that
so there's the kind of things that you
get there but the advantage of that kind
of technologies is that in terms of
rendering uh it costs not that much
because you're pretty much relying on
what the system is able to do and to
provide you and if let's say ios 17 has
a brand new 3d way of holographically
displaying your items on your screen
then it's going to be there
don't give them any new ideas please
[Laughter]
so i don't know about anything anything
there but saying that following what the
system provides is quite important we we
went from skeuomorphism frisom to
metroid designs to flat layouts and
things like that so that's the kind of
things that that needs to happen and
then if you do that that means that
you're really following closely with the
system provides so the most important
example is specifically is
when you're in text box and you press
long press on the text button on ios
there's a little magnifier that happens
to show up on top of what you're trying
to to see so that you can read it better
and you know that comes for free because
you don't need to do anything with
you're using the native controls to do
that so that's some of the frameworks
are doing that kind of rendering so
we're talking about the ui layer we're
going to talk about the underlying
afterward but then there's the other way
the completely opposite of the spectrum
the other one is draw everything
and you treat the screen as a bunch of
pixels
which means that basically when you're
going to be rendering your application
it's going to be looking the same across
platforms you'll be down to the pixel
you know the animation is going to be
the same
the response to the user input is going
to be the same so it's going to be
you know for kind of a
you know nirvana for your designers
because it's going to be very nice for
cross-platforms then
the problem with that approach is that
your users are going to say well that's
not a native application so it may be
to some pundits of the of the space
gonna say well that's a designer
consideration users don't care if their
applications look native or not but
there are power users that are used to
specific behaviors of controls and then
if they're not behaving the same way for
any kind of reason because you know
we know apple fine tunes everything down
to the micro second because they want
their controls to behave in a very
specific way for good reasons most of
the time then if you're drawing
everything yourself then what you can do
is just mimic what happens
on the platforms that you're trying to
target so
that means that you have to follow that
means you have to implement multiple
versions of it you have to implement it
say the cupertino way of displaying
things and then the material way of
doing things in the material v3 version
of things so you know that's lots of
incrementals for this so
kind of a
problem in a sense because you know you
can do lots of stuff with this
and then you can go down to some devices
that don't even have an underlying
system so for instance you go on an iot
device just probably no ui toolkit in
there at all so if you draw everything
yourself then
you're good to go on that kind of
devices because you the only thing that
you need is
pointer xy
location when you touch the screen and
then
the rest is going to be the same as
running on a shiny device that is very
expensive on the other end so
that's where kind of use the best tool
for the job is kind of interesting and
then there are other frameworks that do
in between in between the two which is
kind of use the controls from the
platform
or use the ui toolkit from the platform
but chromeless in a sense so let's say
if you want to have a text box then show
the cursor for the text box but then
don't show anything else
that means that you benefit from
everything that has touch input or
things like that and the interactions
from the system untouched but then if
you want to have a video text box you
can do that because
that's possible because you're you know
the framework is going to be
re-rendering everything but for you and
you don't have to do anything there now
that approach has also its advantages
and disadvantages being in the middle
like this means that there may be things
that are possible in one sense or maybe
there's performance drawbacks so it's
kind of a
choose what's best
for your
scenario because in some cases rendering
everything may make sense on the other
end you know rendering nothing yourself
may make sense just layouts and then
doing in between may make sense because
your scenario makes more sense so that's
the baseline in terms of what's
happening with the ui part of all this
yeah and i mean that's a lot right
also
the one you choose is going to have some
impact so this is one of those areas
where when you're about to make an
irreversible decision it's it's good to
make sure you've spent the time
to ponder these things because
choosing one of these frameworks is
going to have implications for your
teams for the long haul for sure
as far as the more hybrid approaches
that you mentioned you didn't use that
word but you know between the two
extremes of fully native versus draw it
all yourself and then somewhere in in
between
other things come to mind flutter is one
of them
uno platform is one are there others and
with those can you maybe help our
listeners understand maybe what
distinguishes some of those different
frameworks that are trying to solve some
of these same problems
you have many names around this so
maybe your react native is on one side
you have your maui and xamarin forums
you have the react that runs on the web
it's close to react native but not
really then you have blazer on the
microsoft side that does
not yet cross-platform but it's going to
be with maui uno platform which does
all of the above depending on the
platform there are many others like
avalonia that does kind of a rendering
that uses all pixel rendering
so choosing follows platforms depends on
two things the first one is what do you
want to do with your ui in terms of
rendering do you want to have access to
everything by the pixel or do you want
to have access to the system so in terms
of the ui so that's
kind of top-level choice in terms of
what you want to do or an in-between but
with trade-off depending on what you're
trying to get to
then the underlying would be
what's the
language that you want to use
so the actual programming language that
you want to use
it goes from c-sharp to javascript to
typescript depending on the target to
dart to f-sharp to rust in some cases so
it goes very very wide and those
languages depending on what they provide
they don't necessarily provide you a
direct way to get to the underlying
system
so
some do expose the api almost as is so
in c sharp that's the way it is pretty
much you can take some objective c or
swift code to some extent and then
transcode it line by line it's going to
behave pretty much the same way but then
there are others that you use different
techniques that are more chatty or more
loose in terms of typing where you can
interact with the system in in different
ways then there are others where you
just can't do it and then you have to
have a new c plus plus interrupt and
then you do you go to c plus plus and
then or java interrupted things like
that so you can just go directly to the
platform so
it's kind of what's best for you in
terms of do you need to interrupt a lot
with the system
if you do maybe choose one that allows
you to do without too much nuts and
bolts to change and tweaks to make and
you have to factor all this in to make
the choice to determine what kind of
target you want to use i don't know we
wanted to get to some point where we're
able to get access to everything and
with regards to the ui that we're trying
to get to is
depending on the target either we render
everything or we use a hybrid approach
and you know let's say if you want to
run an iot device then uno allows you to
render everything by the pixel but if
you're on an ios and android devices
then it makes more sense because you may
want to have access to a user to do
accessibility and that's where having
access to the hybrid approach allows you
to do this but still now you decide to
be in the nirvana because they can
design it whatever they want so that's
the kind of things that we're trying to
get to to uno so that's pretty much the
landscape in terms of you know very high
level at least
yeah and that's again helpful to kind of
get that broad overview
so there's so many things going on here
that it seems like
in some ways these tools
they might reduce some complexities but
they also can introduce other ones
which complexities would you rather deal
with pick your poison yeah like you
mentioned design nirvana and you know i
think product nirvana is just you know
it runs anywhere and it looks consistent
and it's like what do those words mean
it depends on who is it consistent for
and i was alluding this to the fact that
people are saying well i don't want my
design to be the same everywhere because
i as a user don't want to have to deal
with the ui that doesn't look the same
because i want to use the controls that
have been designed by apple but who am i
to say this am i representing my users
maybe not because my users don't care
and what they want is an application
that works so you design your
applications for your users and not
necessarily for the power users that
designs the applications so that's the
questions to ask is what's your audience
if your audience is a set of developers
maybe you want to do something that you
know uses the native apis or the native
controls because maybe they're going to
be akin to find those differences and
kind of bash you in a way when they're
doing things or because they you know
they expect some system to behave a
specific way now if you're running on a
i don't know banking application
maybe banking is different but let's say
any kind of application end user
application and you want your users to
be at home when they move devices which
is likely to be the case they're going
to be using it from their mobile phone
when they're moving they're moving and
then coming back to the web and then
expect the visual cues to be the same
because they don't want to get lost in
the application so that's kind of things
to consider as well so
where your developers may not be lost in
that regard because they're used to the
kind of differences between and they're
used to get to the differences between
platforms where other users may not so
who's your user basically yeah i know
your audience who's your user and
thinking about particular tools comes to
mind i mean one of the ones that i've
always
thought did a really good job of
consistency is trello
and there's just a ton of consistency
between how it functions in the
different idioms and the different form
factors
and yet that's very much leaning towards
the pixel perfect side of things but
something else i notice about that and
other solutions is when you start
getting away from more of the atomic
controls like check boxes and text boxes
and you start getting to richer controls
that are composed and now have more
behavior that are involved in them as
well
i imagine that's going to draw you to
some design decisions about where you
end up on that spectrum of very pixel
perfect versus taking what the system
already provides for you
that's correct that's correct and you
know
composability is another and this is
another thing being able to get your
controls to do exactly what you want is
something that's very powerful and being
able to create your 3d
video enhanced button with you know
flashy colors that your designer wanted
is something that may not be easy to do
with all platforms and if your intent is
to have this then
you know choose wisely because not
everything allows you to do the kind of
things sure and you said something i i
find funny you said our control should
let us control how things work and
ironically sometimes our controls feel
like they do the opposite they feel like
they are taking control away from me so
it's just
yeah it's you know design is hard new
design and ux it's very difficult to get
to and especially across platforms
because it may not make sense if you're
designing something for touch and then
going to the web you want on the desktop
then it doesn't make sense some touch
interactions don't make sense at all
kind of like the the most prominent
example is hover stuff you're hovering
onto something because you want to you
want to expand or add more content and
it makes sense to hide stuff away and
apple's been permanently
good and bad at doing this because even
on mac os you if you want to
try to get a hold on to the scroll bar
with your mouse
because you want to go down one pixel
because whatever you want to it's very
difficult to get to and it makes sense
on the web on the touch device because
you can touch the screen and move and
then scroll bars and you don't care
about the scroll bar but if you want a
touch screen and then for some reason
you don't you can't scroll with your two
fingers because of whichever item you're
on then
don't move those things away so it's
kind of a difficult way to get to this
and those uxes depending on the platform
need to be thought of and thought
through properly otherwise you're going
to get your user lost yeah and it's
amazing the ways that we can couple the
things that we don't even realize the
very fact that we have on mouse fill in
the blank means that for our entire
careers we have coupled
events to a specific solution which is
mouse
and yet really it's about user
interaction is what you're after and now
with things like touch versus hover
versus these things you see that even
those then are coupled in interesting
ways to design decisions about the form
factor and the idioms of the device that
you're using
and
then you start to wonder and we
shouldn't go here because it'll take us
far afield but just kind of a thought
exercise for the listener is then what
is the right abstraction or maybe the
right's the wrong way what is a broader
abstraction because that's really what
we're hunting for when we talk about
this is
okay this is a useful abstraction and
that's fine but it's also leaky and
coupled in some interesting ways so
what's the next abstraction that we're
looking for it always comes back to the
scenarios for users and for uno
specifically
recently most people that are coming to
us are saying well i want a
desktop
windows application that runs on the web
as well
or i want a mobile application that can
sometimes run on the web but mobile only
because i don't want to publish to the
stores things like that and you're
getting to
design for those specific subsets of the
so the supported apis supported
platforms makes more sense in some cases
to get there and i was talking before
with the the abstraction and things like
that or kind of supported apis it's the
focusability of controls it's something
that you don't really need when you're
on a mobile device and then when you go
back to a desktop then you need that and
if your framework doesn't support this
because it was mainly developed for
mobile then you may have a problem when
when your user starts just tabbing
through to get to the controls that they
want to and uh
leaky or not you're gonna have to
support that somehow because there are
people that are only use the keyboard
and they want to use a mouse or because
they can't you they cannot use a mouse
so that's the very important aspects of
all this so lots of consideration when
choosing a framework
absolutely well let's dive a little more
deep then into uno specifically having
kind of looked more broadly
we've talked a bit about xamarin and
maui and flutter react native i don't
know if you mentioned electron but
that's another one that comes to mind as
well yeah well we could talk about that
one it's actually quite interesting
because uh there wasn't space but with
regards to to uno what we've been trying
to get to is to get to c-sharp ensemble
across platform with reducing the burden
of designing the ui of an application
and and developing the ui of an
application across all those platforms
that we mentioned webassembly being
the biggest driver lately either because
it's the newest one or because it's the
farthest reaching one or the
future proof one i don't know yeah that
remains to be seen that's the remains
yeah it's the promise but still it's
it's getting interesting and you know
lots of things are happening in that
space the w3c
and the implementations that are
happening in the browsers are making
this go a lot faster lately with regards
to all the features they're heading
they added exception handling and cmd so
vectorization for computation they added
everything that goes along with running
webassembly outside of the browser with
interface types and things like that so
lots of things that are happening in
that space and that makes for for very
interesting things like we have a client
that's basically ported his own
application from you know i think it was
12 or 15 years above c-sharp develop and
don't remember exactly how much but the
very very large application that now
runs in the web and kind of the
investment and reuse it's it's just
massive so and they instead they intend
to go to other platforms though the
problem is that the application is very
heavy
you know
desktop applications have a tendency of
being you know data crammed you know
i want to have as much data as like as i
can and that's completely the opposite
of what mobile apps need to be doing
which is i'm showing only what's needed
to be seen and that's what makes those
applications a bit complex to go from
the desktop to the mobile even though
the other way around is a bit easier but
still you have to all those
considerations so that that's the kind
of thing so you know webassembly has
been driving quite a bit from the past
three years and it's still moving
and the good thing is that with regards
to developing on all those platforms is
that we're trying to get to the widest
reaching audience in terms of the apis
that we're trying to implement as well
as the number of platforms and
performance that we're getting there so
we try we're investing a lot into what
linux is able to do with regards to the
skia backhands that we're doing as well
as on ios and android getting as many
features possible implemented there so
still using all the same c-sharp and
dot-net apis and with all the things
that maui team is doing underneath so
we're using everything.net is providing
and maui is sitting on top of this and
we're sitting in the same thing the maui
is doing is using.net for mobile for ios
android mac catalyst and mac os and
we're pretty much using the same api so
we're standing on the shoulders of the
team for that specific part of the
support we're having for mobile so kind
of aiming at a wide range of supported
platforms but still using
net and c-sharp and xaml everywhere so
yes that's what we're trying to do it's
kind of a
large large summary of what we're doing
yeah
and you're keeping linux desktop on the
table oh desktop table sorry excuse the
pun but because my understanding is that
linux desktop is not going to be
supported by maui but uno platform is
continuing to enable delivery of a linux
desktop application as well yeah
definitely i mean we're getting a lot of
requests for getting things to run on
linux for a variety of reasons
whether it's because you know people do
like csharp.net and they want to you'll
be able to develop on their dinner
targets because they don't want to run
on windows or because they have
specialized hardware with regards to
licensing and things like that they want
to run there or because they have
specialized iot devices and they want to
run in that direction and the reason
we're able to do this is because the way
we've been rendering our ui is by using
another internal abstraction or actually
it's a public abstraction but it's
called the composition api and microsoft
has been using this apis to render the
xaml
ui on top of this
and we basically
implemented that part of the api on top
of skia so
is a framework to render pretty much
pixels
in a sense and then we're we're sitting
on top of skia using composition api and
that composition api allows us to do you
know drawing images shapes text
you know with sprites
clipping things like that you know all
sorts of things that you can find in a
retained mode api that renders pixels
that allows us to render things across
platforms and specifically on skia and
everything up top like if you want to
render a button that button is going to
be rendering the same way across
platforms using that kind of apis
yeah that's great and i think if it's
not clear to listeners yet it but it
seems clear just want to make sure
when we're talking about uno platform
while you're while we're using xaml in
this space as an abstraction over ui and
we're using c sharp to build our
application
these applications not only are targeted
for multiple platforms meaning they're
not locked to microsoft or windows or
things of that nature but it's also
possible to develop these applications
if you have a mac or a linux box or a
windows box it's possible for you to do
your development and you can target
these platforms from multiple places
exactly it's all about getting c-sharp
and xaml across platforms so starting
maybe from windows if you want but it's
not necessarily a requirement and then
you can develop from your linux box if
you want using vs code or you can use
github code spaces if you want or git
pod if you want as well so that's all
the kind of development environment that
are available we uno four that was
released a few months ago we added
support for vs code using a new
intellisense and hot reload
support inside of vs code so you can
be helped writing your xaml inside of
visual studio code inside of your gitpod
or github code spaces if you want that's
the kind of scenarios that makes it
interesting yeah that's really great and
speaking of that if any listeners out
there are using github if you haven't
yet found if you're on a mac it's
command period if you're on linux or
windows it's control period
it will open up something very cool i
will leave you to do that yourself and
you will thank me later if you did not
know about it so just control or command
period when you're in a github looking
at code in a repository it's it's pretty
cool so back to uno this it sounds
really fascinating and this isn't
specifically about the platform itself
but you've mentioned a couple times that
you have clients
so i guess there's a business model here
with uno platform so maybe you can speak
about the relationship between the uno
platform itself and then
what keeps uno viable i imagine is
that there's a business model that
allows you to keep building it out and
that's probably good for listeners to
know that there's something driving this
too that it's not just going to
disappear tomorrow so speak to that some
if you will we're basically using the
red hat model which is
hire us to fix the bugs that you've
opened pretty much if i if i sum it up
in that way so the idea is that you can
go on tour github and open issues and
if there is someone that's on the
community and wants to fix it up you
know great or you may want to fix it up
that's good make a contribution and we
can review the pr but then if you don't
have the ability to do that kind of
contribution then you can contact us and
then we're going to be taking a look at
those issues using the paid commitment
and basically what happens is that your
bug or issue or feature request is going
to be bumped up
there are priority lists based on the
clients that we have currently so that
we can fix the issues that you've raised
that's the way we're sustaining
ourselves so
we're multiple clients we have our
parent company inventive which also does
that which uses uno platform so we have
a lot of applications that have been
developed using uno and still being
developed using it so we're making lots
of changes inside of uno and adding
features and and things like that based
based on that so that's the that's
basically the model let's let us know
what you need open issues and then
contact us if you need those issues to
be fixed faster that's great so you're
using it for applications that you're
building for customers
therefore you you're building the tools
that you need to do that and improving
them accordingly and then for those in
the community who want to use it they
can use it because it's free and open
source and if they find a gap i imagine
you accept pull requests under certain
contribution guidelines
and if they don't want to send you a
pull request but they want something to
be upped in the priority list there's a
way that they can go about that as well
that's exactly that so of course you
know accepting contributions is always
something you know specific because when
you accept a contribution then you make
it your own so so it's not because
you've opened the request that we may
accept everything and that's the same
thing with regards to handling open
source and the sustainability model of
every open source project if you open up
a request because if you've done
something
it's not just your time that you could
you have to consider it's the time of
the maintainer that needs to be
looking at your pr
making it
part of the environment in a proper way
and then
live with it
once it's merged in and we know that
maintenance is far more expensive than
implementation by order of magnitude at
least
exactly and if you take a look at the
way cross-platform frameworks work and
especially uno because of the number of
targets that we we do support is that
when you're creating a feature it has to
work
everywhere
and that makes it complicated in terms
of in terms of support so that's why
we've been segmenting everything so that
developers can provide
new partial implementations so let's say
you can implement an api for android
only if you want that is possible we
have a way to indicate to developer that
you know that api that you're trying to
use it's not available on the target you
want to run so that's the kind of things
that are available and you can do that
at runtime if you want to that's the
kind of of things that are possible so
let's say it's not available in specific
version of uno and then you update it
then it becomes available then you can
feature flag it and say now it's
available i can use it so that again the
kind of things that are possible but
anyways the point being that accepting a
pr is a commitment it is no drive by
pull requests oh no well i mean you
can't do a drive by pull request it
doesn't mean that we're going to be
expecting accepting it right and that's
the idea you know more generally with
open source get to know the community
get to know the contributors earn some
trust maybe make some small
things but don't just say here's this
massive pull request and i've moved
everything around and changed everything
and here it's you know take it yeah
exactly so that doesn't work and it's
always the battle of getting to what do
i choose first you know there's that
nice pr that's been implemented for a
while
and that there's another client that's
paid for something so how do i place
priority-wise those and i'm sure the
communities are based in the same way
that are treating their backlog in the
same way using pay clients and open
source contributors and you know having
to deal with that kind of priorities
it's tough in some cases so we're glad
to have a model that works for us but
it's not always possible for everyone to
kind of offer
paid support because if someone pays you
to do something you have to do it so you
can't just accept bluntly the money and
then do not do anything afterwards so
the ecosystem needs to change a bit in
terms of getting you we've seen that
with log4j and the number of emails that
have been sent to the maintainers
requesting or demanding fixes or
come on people you know it's open source
stuff you can't expect all this that's
that's not possible and the net
community has been different in that
sense say we can discuss that one if you
want to if
we have the time but it's been a bit
different in terms of expecting things
around where microsoft has been the
provider of things which is not the case
in other in other communities and has
been shifting
bit by bit over the last 15 years which
which i think has been a good thing
i do wish we had more time to explore
that but we don't i will say though
you've proven one of my things which
i've been kicking around as a theory
going forward which is from now on no
podcast is complete until there's a
reference to log4j so thank you for uh
proving that as and we should just end
it right there because that means the
podcast is over
so for those who aren't familiar we'll
put a link to the show notes for log4j
although i will i will wonder where you
have been for the last three months if
you don't know what's up with the log
for j world but yes open source
generally and there's some great stuff
to explore there maybe in a future
conversation we can dig a little bit
more into open source more generally but
as far as now i know in my research on
uno platform there's some you know some
other integrations you mentioned vds
code i know there's an integration with
sigma which is a design tool that
designers use
and to get closer fidelity between that
design nirvana and the actual
implementation is a reason obviously
that you're delivering that sort of a
solution
what's next for uno platform what are
some big things you're working on say
over the next three to six months
improving performance improving platform
support like new linux support mac os
support.net 6 support because microsoft
is moving you know quite fast in that
direction so you're getting all that
support correct improving your.net 7 for
web assembly is going to be there with
lots of support for performance in aot
for webassembly newer features like we
hope threading that's something that's
going to keep us busy yeah the figma is
going to get keep us busy as well the
figma support where you can design your
things in figma and then export that
into your app to get it running without
any clicks navigation included things
like that so yeah lots of things that
are going to happen during the year
that's for sure great well if our
listeners want to find out more about
what you're up to where can they find
you on on twitter github twitter github
so at the uno platform if i remember
correctly we get the two words there
we're on discord and github discussions
also if they want to ask questions and
to get started you get a platform that
uno slash getting started if i remember
correctly and mostly twitter twitter and
then discord too to discuss things
around and then for you personally on
twitter
i'm on twitter so uh jlabn if you search
my name you're gonna find me and uh
you're happy to discuss you know
crosstalk of things absolutely well it's
been wonderful having you here it's
clear that there's a breadth of
experience behind everything and your
passion is evident
so i appreciate you two giving us kind
of a broad swath of cross-platform ui
generally but we were also able to dive
in a little bit more into what nuno
platform is doing specifically so really
glad you joined me here today on the
show of course thanks for having me okay
this is jeff doolittle for software
engineering radio thanks so much for
listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening